So in this week's videos I've taught you about Named Ranges.
तो इस हफ्ते के वीडियोस में मैने सिखाया है आपको नामित श्रेणी के बारे में |
But, of course, we're still running our Dance studio and the
पर हां, हम अभी भी चला रहे है हमारे नृत्य स्टूडियो को और
ultimate goal of this week's exercises is to actually complete a planning
अंतिम लक्ष्य इस हफ्ते के एक्सर्साइज़स का है ख़तम करना आयोजन
for our Dance studio. So let's have a look at what we've done so far:
हमारे नृत्य स्टूडियो का | तो चलिए देखते है हम अभी तक क्या किए है :
we have improved our formula with use of named range, we've made a data table
हमने हमारा फ़ॉर्मूला को सुधरा है नामित श्रेणी के साथ, हमने एक डेटा टेबल बनाया है
out of the teachers, we have all the information. There's one thing
शिक्षको से, हमारे पास सारा सूचना है | बस एक चीज़
that we still need and that's the availability - what
है जो हमे अभी भी चाहिए और वो है उपलब्धता - कौँसे
teacher can teach on what days of the week, because not all of them are
शिक्षक सीखा सकते है कौँसे दिन हफ्ते के, क्यूंकी सभी कोई
available
नहीं उपलब्ध होंगे
all the time. But we have an issue now here, because in this worksheet
हर दम | पर अभी एक समस्या है हमारे पास इधर, क्यूंकी इस वर्कशीट में
the days of the week are in this
हफ्ते के दिन है इस
direction, whereas the availability is in the other direction.
दिशा में, जब की उपलब्धता है अलग दिशा में |
Well, we can fix that by selecting this data and copying it with Paste Special
वैसे, हम इसे ठीक कर सकते है चुनके इस डेटा को और छपते हुए विशेष पेस्ट से एक
in a transposed way, so all of the data is flipped.
ट्रॅन्सपोज़्ड तरीके से, तो सारा डेटा पलट जाता है |
And now we can copy it back to the original position. But what has happened now
और अभी हम छाप सकते है वापस हमारे पहले वाले जगह पे | पर अभी जो हुआ है वो
is our worksheet has changed, but the named
है हमारा वर्कशीट बदल गया है , पर नामित
ranges have not. So the name is still 'Horizontal levels',
श्रेणी नही बदला है | तो नाम अभी भी 'Horizontal levels' है ,
but in the spreadsheet it doesn't mean Levels anymore,
पर स्प्रेडशीट में इसका मतलब स्तर नही है और
it's actually days of the week now. And this is one of the risks,
यह असलियत में है दिन हफ्ते का | और यह एक जोखिम है
unfortunately, of using named range that I would like to call
दुर्भाग्य से, नामित श्रेणी इस्तेमाल करने का जिसे मैं बुलाना चाहूँगी
the Basmati Effect. Often in your spreadsheet, but also in normal
बासमती प्रभाव | अक्सर आपके स्प्रेडशीट में, और आपके
programming,
प्रोग्रामिंग
it happens that your code changes, your spreadsheet changes,
में यह होता है की आपका कोड बदलता है , आपका स्प्रेडशीट बदलता है
but the values and names you have given to them
पर मूल्य और नाम जो आप दिए रहते है
have not changed, and then you get things like this where you have a container
नही बदलता, और फिर आपको चीज़ें मिलते है जैसे की आपके पास एक पात्र है
saying
कहते हुए
"Rice" but actually it contains cookies. And this is what happens in spreadsheets as
"चावल" पर असलियत में बिस्कुट होगा | और यही हो रहा है स्प्रेडशीट में
well, and this is what has happened now in our example,
भी और हो रहा है हमारे उधारण में,
where we have a name called 'Horizontal Levels', but it actually contains
जहापे हमने नाम दिया है 'Horizontal Levels', पर असलियत में है
days of the week. So your exercise for this week, the first
हफ्ते के दिन | तो आपका एक्सर्साइज़ इस हफ्ते का है, पहला
exercise, is to fix this. I would like you to use the Name Manager to change
एक्सर्साइज़ है , इसे ठीक करना | मैं चाहूँगी आप इस्तेमाल करे Name Manager का
this name into
इस नाम को बदलने में
appropriate name,
एक सही नाम से,
but also to fix the formulas in such a way that you are again
और अपने फ़ॉर्मूला को सुधरे इस तरीके से जैसे आप फिर से
retrieving data, so that you get Xs
डेटा ले रहे है, ताकि आपको Xs मिले
on the spots of the days and the levels. And the second assignment
उन जगहो पे जहा पे दिन और स्तर है | और दूसरा असाइनमेंट
is to actually make the planning - so not just the crosses, but
है सही में आयोजन बनाना - तो सिर्फ़ क्रॉसस नही
actual names for teachers that can teach
बल्कि सही नाम भी है शिक्षकों का जो सीखा सकते है
at a given day for a given level. So that's your assignment, use named ranges but
एक दिए गये दिन पे, दिए हुए स्तर के लिए | तो यह है आपका असाइनमेंट, नामित श्रेणी का इस्तेमाल करना
also
और
all of the things we talked about in previous videos to complete this planning.
उन सब चीज़ों का जो हमने बात किया है पिछले वीडियोस में इस आयोजन को ख़तम करने के लिए |
Good luck!
शुभकामनाएँ|